Thank you for inviting me and thank you everyone for joining and for attending the
talks. So I'm Foutse Khom from the Polytechnique in Montreal well with my team we have been focusing
recently on quality assurance of machine learning enabled systems, right, so the goal
of the research we're trying to do is to allow you guys and the community to design and build
reliable machine learning based systems. And we all know that with this new specificity of the
system, with the dependency of the data, there are much more issues that comes up with the
nature, so we are trying to tackle those issues and issues related to data quality issues
on the specifications, implementations, and so on. So today I will give you a glimpse of some
of the things we have been doing. So machine learning aids have been ready for prime time
so I've been already deploying many systems. I'm pretty sure most of us
have been using some of those systems but they need to be reliable. And typically to
produce the model that we embed in the systems we actually do produce a lot of codes, right, so
this is a typical pipeline for a deep learning systems where you have to produce code to fetch
your data, to automate the learning process, and then you have to train you have to test and validate
until you can deploy. So all through this process we actually writing codes to actually generate
models and then as any type of programs they often fails and they fail a bit differently
from what we do in - what we see in the traditional programs. So contrary to traditional programs the
space of failures for those system is a bit more broader, right, so you can have issues related to
modeling process, so you can have a lot of under-specification issues, and then we also have
implementation issues because we have to actually script all the code that actually automate the
learning process. And we have many issues with data quality, right, so we need to actually be able to
detect those issues. And what I'm trying to share with you is some of the tools that we have been
building to help with this, because we believe that only automation can actually help going through
this process, right - if you have been trying to play with some model you can know that debugging
a machine learning pipeline can be actually very tricky because sometimes the difference between a
state-of-the-art model and a very poor performing model can be as simple as the learning rates, right.
So it's very difficult to actually find those knobs when you try to trick the model so we try to
automate this. So what do we do? So we in this talk I will talk about two approach that we propose.
One is based on static analysis so we brought static analysis to the problem.
Why we thought about this, because then we all know that it's quick, right, it's a bit cheaper and it
can be very effective if it's done correctly upfront. So we have a tool that we built which
is Neural Lens which is actually pretty effective and I actually encourage you to try it out, right.
So the tool can actually have been tested so you have the detail in the paper - I won't talk about the
detail in the paper - but what I can say, is more how the tool works. So how did we build the tools?
So the tool rely on two key components, so we have a meta model of the learning program that we had
to build, right, and then we also had a taxonomy of typical faults in a deep learning program. So
in the tool we basically automate the detection of this faults based on the representation of a
deep learning program that we built, based on this meta model, right. Simple. Okay so the workflow
looks like this - so if you have a program and then you want to use our tool, basically what
we do is, we extract from your program all the different features and components that we need to
comply with the specification of the meta model, then we built a representation of your program,
and then based on our set of rules that we actually specify to detect the different issues,
we can actually run detections on the program and provide a set of checks. And it works and it's
pretty fast, okay, but the problem with this is that with static analysis we can't really tackle
the interaction with the data and the dynamicity that's in the process, right. So to help with
that aspect we try something else that we all do: dynamic analysis. So we decided to actually
explore - what do you do - we decide to inspect the training process of the program and extract
information about the behavior of the program during the training process, and based on this
information we could actually check certain specific property that could be a signal of problem
with the training model, right. So we have this approach, which is also pretty effective - we
have been compared actually with search meta which does a pretty similar thing, and the good news is
that this approach does a bit better, so I actually encourage you to try it out. It can detect 30% more
backs than actually search meta we were kind of forced to compare this for the paper, otherwise
they wouldn't accept the paper, so what do some of the rules that we actually rely on looks like?
So we - the tool implements a variety of checks, right, so some of the checks can be as simple as
checking for parameter related issues or more complex optimization related issues, right, so an
example of parameter related issue you can check untrained parameters and this is very easy to
change right so you can extract information during the training process and then just
perform some verifications, right, some comprising. And then an example of activation related issues
so we can check the ranges right so this is a common if you have been trying deep learning
problem you can you know that this is something that happened sometime very frequently and then
the two can actually report this for you pretty easily right. We also have a lot of checks related
to optimization problems, so you can check if you are fitting the - the data sample for a while if you
are having any vanishing gradients if you have an unstable gradient and so on. So all the checks have
been implemented in the tool I strongly encourage you to try out and the flow is very simple so
there is a small overhead that comes with using the tool because we're actually instrumenting your
process so we're extracting information during the training process so that is on overhead that
comes with that, but through the experimentation and validation that we did the average is actually
stretchable manageable. Okay, so try the tools and that is it for me I guess.
So I wanted to raise your attention about failures occurring frequently in those systems
and the fact that the space of failure in this system is actually pretty large compared to
traditional systems, and that we actually need automation to navigate this space. And hopefully
these tools that we're actually building and releasing will actually help us to avoid those
pitfalls and maybe stay out of the float I think this is from Mike. So any questions?
So that's it.